Finding Aid for Jane Briggs Hart papers, ca. 1925 -1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jane Briggs Hart papers circa 1925-1996
Hart, Jane Briggs.
2010191 Aa 2
Aviator and wife of the late Senator Philip A. Hart. Scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, and papers documenting her life as wife of Senator Philip A. Hart, her family life, and to a lesser extent, her aviation activities.
4 linear feet in 3 boxes and 11 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Jane B. Hart (donor no. 10415 ) in September, 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jane B. ("Janey") Hart is an aviator and wife of the late Senator Philip A. Hart. Jane Hart was born in Detroit, October 20, 1921, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Walter O. Briggs. She attended the Academies of the Sacred Heart in Detroit, Grosse Pointe, and Torresdale, Pennsylvania, and Manhattanville College in New York City. In 1970, she received her BA in anthropology from George Washington University.
Jane Hart was married June 19, 1943, to Philip A. Hart who then was a captain in the U.S. Army. They met when he was her brother's roommate at Georgetown University. The Harts had eight children: Ann, Jane Cameron, Walter, James, Michael, Clyde, Mary Catherine, and Laura Elizabeth. The Harts resided in Birmingham (Oakland County) until 1955, when Philip Hart became Michigan's Lieutenant Governor and the family moved to Lansing. In 1958, Philip Hart was elected to the United States Senate. He served nearly three full terms, resigning in 1976 because of poor health. Philip Hart died shortly after he left the Senate, in December of 1976.
Jane Hart was active in civic affairs and women's rights, and she shared her husband's interest in government and political activities. She was active in her husband's political campaigns and served as vice chairman of the Oakland County Democratic Committee. She was a founding member of the National Organization for Women, and served as board member and national convention delegate for the Birmingham League of Women Voters. She was charter vice president of the Guild of the Pontiac Urban League, a life member of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, a trustee of the Michigan 4-H Foundation, and a member of the board of the Sister Elizabeth Kenny Foundation.
Jane Hart earned her first pilot's license during World War II, after two years as a member of the Red Cross Motor Corps. Her interest in aviation has continued throughout her life; she owned and flew a twin engine six passenger Aero-Commander 500A, and she was the first licensed female helicopter pilot in Michigan. She was a captain in the Civil Air Patrol, a member of the Flying Farmers of Michigan, and a participant in several national cross-country air races.
In the early 1960s, Jane Hart was chosen to be part of the Lovelace Foundation's Woman in Space Program, a privately-funded project testing women pilots for astronaut fitness. She was one of only 13 women (the Mercury 13) to pass the rigorous physical tests developed by NASA to select their astronauts. Despite the test results, the women were not selected for space flights. She and Jerrie Cobb, the first candidate to qualify for astronaut training, went on to campaign in Washington for continuation of the program.
The Jane B. Hart papers include materials that document the life of Philip and Jane Hart, Philip Hart's political career, and Jane Hart's aviation and her role in the effort to include women in the space program. The collection consists of four series: Scrapbooks, Audiovisual, Personal Papers, and Inscribed Volumes.
Subjects:
Hart, Jane Briggs.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Legislators' spouses.; Michigan--Politics and government--1941-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-1960.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Women air pilots--Michigan.; Women astronauts--United States--History.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Air pilots--Michigan.; Hart, Jane Briggs.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Legislators--United States.; Legislators' spouses.; Politics and government--United States.; Women--Political activity--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Scrapbooks circa 1925-1980
  The Scrapbooks contain clippings and photographs documenting Philip Hart's political career, Jane Hart's aviation activities, and her advocacy of the inclusion of women in the space program.
  - Clippings (with occasional letters) relating to the Hart family and Phil Hart's political career in Michigan 1943-1953 (Volume 1)
  - Clippings relating to Michigan politics and to Phil Hart's work as Michigan Lieutenant Governor 1957 (Volume 2)
  - "This is Your Life Janey Hart," 1958 (Volume 3)
    (include clippings with occasional photographs relating to Jane Hart and to Phil Hart's campaign for the US Senate)
  - Clippings and photographs circa 1925-1961 (Volume 4)
    (include Jane Hart as child, equestrian photos, and Jane Hart situated near airplane)
  - Clippings (with occasional photograph) relating to politics 1963-1964 (Volume 5)
    (includes clippings related to Jane Hart's work to include women in the space program)
  - Album containing letters, clippings, and photographs from Philip A. Hart Testimonial Dinner on occasion of Israel's 16th anniversary sponsored by the Detroit Israel Bond Committee May 24, 1964 (Volume 6)
  - Clippings (with occasional letter and publication) relating to national politics 1964-1965 (Volume 7)
    (includes clippings on Jane Hart's aviation activities and women in space)
  - Clippings (with occasional letter and publication) relating to national politics 1965-1966 (Volume 8)
    (includes photos and clippings related to Jane Hart's return to college)
  - Volume of letters from dignitaries upon occasion of Phil Hart's retirement from the US Senate March 14, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Album of photocopied clippings and letters from 1930-1933 and given to Jane Hart on the occasion of the first Philip A. Hart Memorial Lectureship and the dedication of the Philip A. Hart Moot Court Room, Georgetown University, September 17, 1980 (Volume 9)
- Audiovisual 1943-1981
  The Audiovisual series includes photograph albums and loose photographs of the Hart family, the Hart's wedding photos, Philip A. Hart's appearances at government and public events, and Jane Hart's aviation and equestrian activities. The series also includes a video of the dedication of the Philip A. Hart Senate Office Building in 1988, and an audio tape of a radio program in which Ann Hart (a daughter) discusses her participation in Eugene McCarthy's presidential campaign in 1968.
  - Photograph Albums
    - Jane Hart on horseback as part of equestrian performance 1931-1942 (Volume 10)
    - Wedding album of Philip and Jane Hart June 19, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Jane Hart and friends in or near airplanes 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - Baby album: include photo of Phil Hart with baby (perhaps first-born) circa 1945 (Volume 11)
    - Album of snapshots, some from costume party, others of family settings circa 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Album of family portraits and of holiday greetings featuring the Hart family circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1)
  - Loose photographs
    - Photographs circa 1930s-1976 (Box 2)
      (includes portrait of Jane Hart and photos of Phil Hart and Lyndon Johnson on occasion of signing of Civil Rights Act)
    - Photographs: Jane and Phil Hart portraits, wedding photos, and miscellaneous photos 1943-1960s (Box 3)
      (includes photo of Jane Hart in Red Cross vehicle, and with an airplane)
    - Photographs: Hart family portraits and holiday greetings featuring the family circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3)
      (includes several negatives and transparencies)
    - Photographs: Hart family portraits and snapshots circa 1960s-1981 (Box 3)
    - Photographs: Philip A. Hart political and public events 1954-1976, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Loose scrapbook pages 1961-1968 (Box 3)
  - Other Audiovisual Material
    - Fred Gale "Comment" program, WWDC-AM/FM March 15, 1968 (interview with Ann Hart and others about their work on Eugene McCarthy's presidential campaign), 7 in.; reel-to-reel audio tape; 2 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 3)
      (2 CD use copies are available)
    - Hart family photographs circa 1970s-1980s, CD-R; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 3)
    - Dedication of the Philip A. Hart Senate Office Building 1988, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 3)
- Personal Papers 1943-1996
  The small Personal Papers series includes clippings about Philip A. Hart's time in the Senate and memorials and tributes following his death, clippings about Jane Hart and the Hart family, several letters written by Jane Hart and Ann Hart, and miscellaneous papers related to Philip Hart's political career and Jane Hart's work to include women in the space program.
  - Letters from Jane Hart in France 1958 (Box 3)
  - Letters from Ann Hart in Spain and Germany 1965 (Box 3)
  - Jane Hart interview transcript 1981 (Box 3)
    (interview conducted as part of G. Mennen Williams and Nancy Quirk Williams Oral History Project)
  - Materials related to women in aviation and space 1962, 1986 (Box 3)
    (includes Jane Hart's testimony before the Congressional Committee on Science and Aeronautics)
  - Manhattanville College reunion booklet 1993 (Box 3)
  - Clippings on Jane Hart and Hart children 1943, 1958-1977 (Box 3)
  - Clippings on Phil Hart's death and memorials 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Congressional Record, August and Sept 1976 (Box 3)
    (includes tributes to Phil Hart)
  - Memorials and tributes to Phil Hart 1976-1977, 1996 (Box 3)
    (includes letter from Ted Sorensen)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to Phil Hart's political career 1954-1975, undated (Box 3)
  - Resolutions and certificates 1943-1982 (Box 2)
- Inscribed Volumes
  The final series, Inscribed Volumes, contains miscellaneous books autographed or inscribed by the author to Phil and Jane Hart.
  - Alexander, Shana The Astonishing Elephant (Box 3)
    (inscribed to Jane Hart by author)
  - Breslin, Rosemary Not Exactly What I Had in Mind (Box 3)
    (autographed)
  - Buffa, Dudley W. Union Power and American Democracy (Box 3)
  - Reuther, Walter P. Selected Papers (Box 3)
    (inscribed to Phil Hart by author)
  - Schroeder, Pat Champion of the Great American Family (Box 3)
  - Schwartz, Herman The Burger Years (Box 3)
    (inscribed to Jane Hart by editor)